<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An humble representation of the seamens misery in the loss and abuse of them in their payment, and their being oftentimes extorted out of the one half of it by some, and cheated of it all by others with the mistery of some officers and masters, humbly represented to His Majesty, and the two most honourable houses, the Lords and Commons of England in Parliament assembled ...</title>
            <author>Hodges, William, Sir, 1645?-1714.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44082</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2331</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17273</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12864527</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12864527</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94714</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44082)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94714)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 384:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An humble representation of the seamens misery in the loss and abuse of them in their payment, and their being oftentimes extorted out of the one half of it by some, and cheated of it all by others with the mistery of some officers and masters, humbly represented to His Majesty, and the two most honourable houses, the Lords and Commons of England in Parliament assembled ...</title>
                  <author>Hodges, William, Sir, 1645?-1714.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>All letters signed: William Hodges.</note>
                  <note>Last communications signed: Hermitage-Bridge, Feb. 22, 1694.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from BM.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Royal Navy --  Pay, allowances, etc.</term>
               <term>Sailors --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94714:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>An Humble Repreſentation of the</hi> Seamens <hi>Miſery in the Loſs and Abuſe of them in their Payment, and their being oftentimes Extorted out of the one half of it by ſome, and Cheated of it all by others; with the Miſtery of ſome Officers and Masters, Humbly Repreſented to His Majesty, and the Two most Honourable Houſes, the</hi> Lords <hi>and</hi> Commons <hi>of</hi> England <hi>in Parliament Aſſembled, Humbly ſheweth,</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>To the Moſt Excellent Majeſty of King <hi>WILLIAM</hi> the Third.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>May it Pleaſe Your Moſt Gracious Majeſty,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IF Kings on Their Thrones be as the Sun in the Firmament.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt</hi> then, That was a Happy Day to theſe Nations, and indeed to all <hi>Europe,</hi> when God cauſed You to Ariſe and Shine on theſe Three Nations.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> None but Evil Spirits and Beaſts of Prey can wiſh for Your being Set, that they may walk about, and Devour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> As Your Gracious Influence doth in it ſelf ſhine Comfortably unto all theſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: So,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Thoſe that by Reaſon of any Clouds or Groſs Vapours have the Influence of Your Majeſtyes Mercy (I was a going to ſay, and Juſtice alſo) hid from them, have the more Cauſe ſadly to lament; of which Number is many Poor Diſtreſſed Seamens Families: And I will Avouch for the Seamen of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> they have been hearty and truely ſincere in the Intereſt of Your Majeſty and theſe Nations, as any ſort of Men whatever, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving never loſt you one Ship this War for want of their Fighting, if they could but be led on, although there have been ſo many brave Ships loſt by Cowardice, Folly, or otherwiſe this War, as no Age before ever ſaw the like. And,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> I hope as Your Majeſties Gracious Influence hath ſhined on the Commanders Good and Bad, to double their and the Officers Pay, which will Coſt Your Majeſty more in Two Years time extraordinary, than all the Cuſtoms came to in the Two Reigns of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> as by the Accounts of the Exchequer, and the Pay-Books in <hi>Broad-ſtreet</hi> will appear; and in the mean while, inſtead of the Poor Miſerable Seamen being doubled in their Pay, they are doubled many of them in their Miſery, being made run from their being ſet Sick on Shore; but I hope, if the Repreſenting their Caſe can pierce thorow the Clouds, and come to Your Gracious Sight, it will appear that they were very groſs Clouds that could hinder either Juſtice or Mercy from Shining on ſo Faithful and Uſeful Loving Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects as the Seamen of <hi>England</hi> have been, and will be, for all theſe Darkneſſes that have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallen their Families: And may it pleaſe Your Moſt Gracious Majeſty, If I can ſerve God and Your Majeſty, and the Intereſt of theſe Nations, in Repreſenting the Caſe, I will Rejoyce; And if for my Unworthyneſs I ſhould meet with Reproof, I will in Doing and Suffering, Remain,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Majeſties Faithful, Loving Subject and Servant, <hi>WILLIAM HODGES.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>To the Moſt Honourable, The LORDS <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Temporal,</hi> in <hi>Parliament</hi> Aſſembled.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>May it Pleaſe Your Lordſhips,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Did Humbly make bold to Repreſent ſome of the Seamens Miſeries laſt Year to your Lordſhips, and ſome of Your Lordſhips were Graciouſly Pleaſed to le<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it be Repreſented to His Majeſty; and there hath been ſince much Mercy ordered out to many Thouſands of them: but there hath been a Load of Miſery fallen on ſome Thouſands ſince, if not thrown on them, which I intend in ſome meaſure humbly to Repreſent, if it be worthy of Your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:94714:2"/>Peruſal; and Your Lordſhips ſhall find they have been ſo Faithful to His Majeſty, that they deſerve at leaſt to be ſaved from Ruine; and therefore that His Majeſty might be ſought to for Relief, I ſhall Rejoyce: But however, I will beg Your Lordſhips Pardon, and Remain,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>His Majeſties Faithful Subject, and Your Lordſhips moſt Humble Servant, WILLIAM HODGES.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>To the Honourable, The <hi>Knights, Citizens,</hi> and <hi>Burgeſſes</hi> in <hi>Parliament</hi> Aſſembled,</head>
               <opener>Humbly ſheweth,</opener>
               <p>I Did Humbly Preſume the laſt Year to Repreſent to Your Honours the Miſery of the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Families for want of their Pay; and Your Honours did ſo Provide for their Relief, that they have been more happy in their Payments, ſince that there having been a Large Supply of Money ſent into the Pay-Office for that purpoſe, to the Rejoycing of the Hearts of Thouſands: But now there is other Miſeries either fallen on them, or thrown on them; there being ſome Thouſands ſet Sick on the Shore, and are made Run: And there are ſome other Miſeries have attended the Miſerable Seamen before, that are Humbly Repreſented to Your Honours for Relief; And alſo, I have Repreſented, how it is poſſible His Majeſty and theſe Nations may be Cheated, and the Seamen Abuſed and Cheated alſo: And if Your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours can find out a way to Relieve the Miſerable Seamen, and to ſave them and the Nation from being Cheated of Fifty or a Hundred Thouſand Pound a Year, it will be worth Your Honours Trouble: But however, I Repreſent their Caſe to Your Honours, I do not intend to Repreſent it ſo among the Seamen; for it is well they do not know their Miſery together; and while they know it ſeparately, they only do bemoan it, and groan under it apart: And if Your Honours think it worth Your while to Peruſe their Caſe, I will, as laſt Year, Print enough to give every one of Your Honours one, but not one to go about the Streets: For if I do not miſtake my own Heart, what I do, is to ſerve God, and my King, and Countrey, without either hope of Profit, or any Prejudice to any whoſe Knavery may be ſmelt out by my Simple Diſcourſe: And I am ſure, there is none that are Honeſt can be Prejudiced by what I Repreſent of Knavery, no more than thoſe who are Honeſt Men, and go to <hi>Aldgate</hi>-Church, where there is a great Crowd, can be prejudiced by the ſaying of any, that there is ſometimes Pick-Pockets amongſt them; for ſo there is, to the loſs of Honeſt Mens Money ſometimes in that Church, and other Churches and Meeting-Houſes; and more then that, ſome Friends of mine have had their Pockets pickt at the Aſſizes in <hi>Kent,</hi> in the very Court where the Judges ſate: But it may be, I ſhall preſcribe a Remedy, that if well applyed, would clear away the Thieves out of the Nation in a few Years: But I humbly Intreat Your Honours Pardon for this great Troubling of You, and I do aſſure Your Honours,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>I am, His Moſt Gracious Majeſty, King <hi>WILLIAM</hi>'s Faithful Subject, and Your Honours Humble Servant, WILLIAM HODGES.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>To His Moſt Gracious <hi>MAJESTY,</hi> And, To the Two Moſt Honourable Houſes, The LORDS and COMMONS in <hi>Parliament</hi> Aſſembled,</head>
               <opener>Humbly ſheweth,</opener>
               <p>THAT the Laſt Year, the Loyal and Faithful Seamen of <hi>England</hi> having met with great Diſappointment in many of their Payments, and it being Humbly Repreſented to His Majeſty and Your Honours, there was ſo great Relief Ordered, that Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands have cauſe to Bleſs God for at this day, and to Return Thanks to His Majeſty and Your Honours; and there being ſome Hardſhips and Miſeries on the Seamen at preſent, which it may be ſuppoſed, have not been truely Repreſented to His Majeſty and Your Honours; and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:94714:3"/>therefore may with the greater hopes be expected to be Relieved: And ſome of them are as follows.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> There is many of them that are turned from Ship to Ship, that have Money due in Three Ships, to this day unpaid.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Some Thouſands have been ſet on Shoar Sick, and many of them either Dying or Continuing Sick; And ſome ſent to the Hoſpitals, and yet for not going on Board their Ships again, they are made a Run.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Some that their Ships going away before they were well, and they not being able to get to their Ships, have gone on Board of other Ships, and they are made a Run, although ſtill in His Majeſties Service.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Some that have been preſt away while their own Ships have been in the Dock to mend, or otherwiſe, and carried on Board of others of His Majeſties Ships, have yet been made a Run.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Sometimes when Men are either a Preſſing, or on Shoar about the Ships Buſineſs, or with the Captains Leave, are by the Clerk of the Check made Run.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixthly,</hi> Sometimes when a Man hath Twenty Pound due in a Ship, and is diſcharged by the Captain, and hath a Ticket given him for his Pay, yet by the Clerk of the Check he is made Run, although he was Entred the next day on Board another Ship.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seventhly,</hi> It is of late it ſeems ſo ſeverely carryed on againſt the Poor Seamen, that if they have an R — on the laſt Ship, they are made Run for the other Ships they were in before.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eighthly,</hi> By that means it is not ſafe for Landlord, or Chandler, or Tradeſman to truſt the Families of the Diſtreſſed Seamen for Rent, Cloaths or Bread, ſince if that a Seamen be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, he may be turned over out of the firſt Ship into another Ship; and in the ſecond Ship he may fall Sick, and be ſet on Shoar, and there dye, and he made Run; as is viſible now right or wrong, to put a <hi>Q.</hi> or an <hi>R.</hi> on their Names; and at Pay-day, if none were there before, if they Return not to their Ships again, and that they cannot do, if Sickneſs or Death Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents; or alſo, if their Ships be gone to the <hi>Streights,</hi> or to the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> that it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to follow them; or if they are preſt on Board of other Ships, and looſe their Pay for the former, it will be Miſerable, and look like great Cruelty.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ninthly,</hi> Another Miſery is, that the Captains of Ships make out Tickets for ſeveral of them, and keep them; and the poor Wretches that are the Seamens Wives, know not of them; and ſo are put by their Pay at Pay-day, for the Captains or others having their Tickets.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tenthly,</hi> There is no Law made to puniſh the Captains for keeping the Tickets, whereby the Miſery of the Seamen is Great and Deplorable, and like to Continue, if not Relieved.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eleventhly,</hi> When Seamen are turned over into other Ships, the Captain of the laſt Ship de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands the Tickets for the other Ship; and ſo if the Seamen would get either Bread for their Families or Cloaths for themſelves on Credit of their other Pay they have been ſometimes hindred, and ſometimes loſe the Payment at Recals alſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Twelfthly,</hi> When the Seamen ſee that thoſe that go to <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> have Six or Seven Pound a Voyage; and it may be it is Earned in a Moneth; and others in Merchants Ships have Fifty Shillings or Three Pound the Moneth, and their Families have a Conſtant Supply; and they that ſerve the King, ſo ſerved by one Miſery or another, or by their Captains Knavery their Tickets detained, then it may be ſome Seamen do in good earneſt run away; and under the Notion of theſe running away, there are ſome Thouſands of others made Run, or have a <hi>Q.</hi> put to their Pay, which muſt be Petitioned for, or their Pay loſt, as if they were run indeed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirteenthly,</hi> It is in the power of the Captain, or the Captains Clerk, or the Clerks of the Office, or the Clerk of the Check, or the Purſer to put a <hi>Q.</hi> or an <hi>R.</hi> on any poor Seamans Pay, and that is as bad as an Execution almoſt; ſince if a Man have a <hi>Q.</hi> or an <hi>R.</hi> in one Book, and ſtands clear in all the reſt, is made Run in all the Reſt, ſometimes; and none that I ever heard of, is called in queſtion why the <hi>Q.</hi> or <hi>R.</hi> was put on</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourteenthly,</hi> The poor Seamens Wives or Friends, it may be, know not of it until Pay-Day, and then loſe their Payment; and after waiting Two or Three Years, are forc't to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin again; and it may be, they live in <hi>Scotland,</hi> or in the <hi>North</hi> or <hi>Weſt</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> and when they hear of it, to come up to Petition, it may be the poor Wretches are,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifteenthly,</hi> Forced to wait Ten or Twelve Weeks to get a Petition anſwered; and at laſt, it may be, they cannot ſend to the <hi>Streights</hi> or <hi>Weſt-Indies</hi> for to have Certificates from the Commanders, or to get the Tickets from their Commanders, and ſo are in danger to loſe all at laſt, and that is poor Relief, and I fear the Cryes will Reach to Heaven.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixteenthly,</hi> After the Seamen have had all this Affliction, and thoſe that have truſted them, are many of them Broken and gone away, yet there are ſome Commanders ſo unreaſonable; as to hinder thoſe that truſted them, from coming on Board to Receive their Money at Pay-Day, but ſet Centeryes to threaten to ſhoot thoſe who come on Board to look for their own Money.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seventeenthly,</hi> Some Commanders have ſet Centeryes to keep away thoſe from coming on Board that had Cloaths to ſell for the Seamen at Pay-Day, threatning to ſhoot them, or ſink their Boats, whereby the Seamen cannot ſafely be truſted before Pay-Day; neither furniſhed
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94714:4"/>ſo Plentifully and Cheap, as they might at Pay-Day to the Diſcouragement of Trade, and hindrance of the Seamens having Choice of Goods.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eighteenthly,</hi> A Tradeſman might have gotten a Clerk to Receive the Money due on Bills from Seamen at Pay Day, for One Shilling the Pound; And,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nineteenthly,</hi> The poor Seamens Wives might have had their Husbands Pay Received by a Clerk at Pay-Day for One Shilling in the Pound, and now the Clerks are hindred from that, whereby a poor Seamans Wife may go to <hi>Portſmouth</hi> and wait a Moneth, ſpend Forty Shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings going and coming, and give One as much more to look after, and provide for her Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in that time, to Receive a Tickets Money of Five Pound, that might have been Received for Five Shillings by the Clerks.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Twentiethly,</hi> The Seamens Families were in ſuch great Diſtreſs before, that they ſold their Pay ſome of them at half loſs, and there being none Appointed to hear their ſad Complaints, and to Relieve them againſt ſuch as Extorted their Pay at half loſs, neither to call thoſe Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains to Account that kept their Tickets, or Received their whole Pay wrongfully. Others ſince that have Extorted their Pay at half loſs ſince; and alſo ſome Commanders have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained their Tickets ſtill, although I am afraid the Groans and Cryes of their Miſery hath cryed in the Ears of God and Man; and it could never be ſuppoſed, that they that ſold their Pay at half loſs could ſerve ſo freely next time, ſeeing none regarded to Relieve them.</p>
               <p>21ly, There hath been near Twenty Thouſand hath dyed in Their Majeſties Service ſince this War, as by the ſeveral Ships-Books will appear, if examined, by the Sword or Sickneſs; many of whom have been made Run, and ſome that have had their Runs taken off with great difficulty or loſs: And if Your Honours would conſider, how the Miſery in ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects do far exceed the Miſery of the other Poor in <hi>England;</hi> the Families of poor Labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers in City and Countrey, have,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Their Wages commonly once a Week, or once a Moneth; the Seamen ſometimes none in Four Years. And,</p>
               <p n="2">2. Other poor Women can many times in the City and Countrey go to their honeſt Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters or Miſtreſſes Houſes, and have many a good Meals Meat in a Year, yea, it may be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in a Week; But the poor Families of the Seamen, though they have the beſt Maſter on this ſide of Heaven, yet His Houſe will not hold them all; and ſo if they have neither Money nor Credit, may ſtarve; unleſs the Pariſhes keep them: And One in particular I knew, that by relation, as appeared after ſhe was dead, did periſh, and to the ſhame of he that was then Church-Warden of <hi>Shadwell;</hi> he would not Support her, becauſe as he preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, ſhe had not payd Scot and Lot to the Pariſh; and at the ſame time ſhe Owed me Ten Pound; and I Lent her more Money while Sic<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, but knew not her Caſe ſo Bad and ſo Extreme Miſerable, until after her Death; and her Husband in a Man of War Three Years, and I was forced to lay down more Money to Bury her, to have her Carried out of the Houſe, her Goods not being all worth Six Shillings: And I ſuppoſe, the laſt week, I being ordered by the Right Honourable the <hi>Lord Mayor</hi> to ſee His Majeſties Gift diſtributed to the Poor in our little Precinct: In going round our poor place, there was near a Thouſand to receive Relief, beſides Children; of which, and others not Relieved, although very poor, I ſuppoſe we have near Three Thouſand, and great part Seamens Families, exceeding poor; and we have but about a Thouſand Houſes in our Precinct: But the poor Seamens Families are ſometimes Four or Five in a Houſe at our end of the Town, very poor; as there is Four or Five Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of others that are Richer, ſometimes Lodging in a Houſe in <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> and <hi>London;</hi> and I ſuppoſe we have Two Hundred Families, all whoſe Goods, if ſold together would hardly yield Twenty Shillings the Family; therefore the Miſery and Poverty, and the Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of the Seamen is exceeding great, and their Caſe very deplorable, and to be ſincerely laid to heart. And I bleſs the Lord, I have done my part to Aſſiſt them this many Years; and moſt eſpecially, to Aſſiſt them in the Service of Their Majeſties and theſe Nations; and in doing that, have loſt by near Three Hundred of them, as by my Books will appear. But yet if they ruine me, I am ſtill by the Providence of God ſtirred up to plead their Cauſe, and they know it not; neither are like to do: And now I will ſhew Your Honours, that ſince this War I might have oppreſſed the Seamen ſo much, as to have gotten ſome Thouſands of Pounds by the Means following; and if the Pay-Books be ſearched, it will appear I have Received of their Pay, to the Number of near a Thouſand Men; and if my own Books be Examined, I have truſted them ſome Thouſands of Pounds; And as to what I have truſted, I can appeal to my own Conſcience, that I know not, that one with another, I did take more by Six pence in the pound profit on truſt, than others did ready Money; and for their Tickets that I payd ready Money for, I do not know, that for the whole time I bought above One in Ten of any Seaman for above Two Shillings and Six pence in the pound profit; whereas, had I extorted in truſting. I might have gotten, it may be, a Thouſand Pound extraordinary that way; and had I bought at Eight or Ten Shillings in the pound profit, I might have made a Thouſand pound Three Thouſand in the firſt Year and halfs time; and the ſaid Three Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand at leaſt Seven or Eight Thouſand in the reſt of the time; and ſo have gotten a Confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Damnable deal of Money out of the Miſeries of the Seamen; yea, gotten the Devil and all; enough to ſend my ſelf to Hell in the getting, and my Poſterity there in the ſpending of it: And it is not for nothing, that ſome that were hardly worth a Penny before the War, are
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:94714:5"/>now worth Hundreds or Thouſands out of the Seamens Pay; and that could, it may be, buy Thirty Eight Pound for Eighteen, and pay them down but Twelve; and let them truſt for the other Six until after the whole Money was paid, and then let them threaten to put them to trouble before they got the other Six. May it pleaſe Your Honours, I have conſidered of my ſad Expreſſions before; but if there were a Committee Appointed to hear the Seamens Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints, and their Families, and that they ſhould have Relief of all that hath been Extorted from them above Two or Three Shillings in the Pound for the Year 1689, and 1690, and above Four Shillings, or at moſt, above Five for all that hath been Extorted out of their Pay, ſince you might hear ſo ſad a Diſcovery that hardly the World can parallel: And I fear, If Your Honours do not Ariſe for the Cry of the Poor, and the Sighing of the Needy, I fear the Lord will; for he hath promiſed it in the 12th. <hi>Pſalm,</hi> and the 5th <hi>verſe.</hi> And for the Poor Miſerable Seamen to be Ruined in their Pay by thoſe who buy it at half loſs, and were almoſt Beggars before the War; ſome of them ſeems to me to be like what that Wiſe King <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaid, <hi>That when the Poor oppreſſed the Poor, it was as a Sweeping Rain that left no food. Prov.</hi> 8.23. And it is a Comfort to me, that when others have Raiſed their Eſtates on the Seamens Miſery, I can with a good Conſcience beg of His Majeſty and all Your Honours for the ſake of Chriſt, and for His Majeſties ſake, and for the Nations ſake, to call thoſe to account that have Cheated the Poor Miſerable Seamen; and for the many Hundreds I have received their Pay, if there be One in Ten that I have had above Half a Crown in Twenty Shillings Profit for all Money paid them, let me Anſwer to any one of them that will call me in Queſtion: And if the Seamen once hear that they may have Relief, they or their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies will readily Complain; and let them who have Cheated them of all, or part, be made Examples of, that all <hi>Iſrael</hi> may hear and fear, and do no more ſo wickedly; and if any have Cheated them of half, and afterward made them over to others at full Value, let the firſt be puniſhed for their Offence, and the laſt only for what is his Tranſgreſſion: And now I will ſhew Your Honours how I could have Cheated His Majeſty many wayes, if I had been Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in ſeveral Offices as follows, <hi>Viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If I were a Captain of a Ship, I could, if none did provide a Remedy againſt it, Cheat him as followeth, <hi>Viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> I could Cheat Him of the greateſt part of my Service, that is, run to and again, and hardly meet an Enemy to fire a Gun againſt in Two or Three Years; although at the ſame time, and all the time, a Merchant Ship ſhould hardly ſtir without Convoy, but ſhe ſhould meet an Enemy, and be taken.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> If I had Three Hundred Men in my Ship, and Forty or Fifty run away, I could then make out Tickets for them, and receive their Pay; and that might Cheat my Honeſt Maſter of 300<abbr>
                     <hi>l</hi>
                  </abbr> And I never call'd to Account for it perhaps.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It may be, as many more would dye, and their Families knew not where they were; and I could Cheat their Families, and receive their lay, 250<abbr>
                     <hi>l</hi>
                  </abbr> Deviliſh Profit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> It may be, ſeveral Maſters of Ships would give me Three or Four Guineas a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece for Seamen; And they would alſo give me their Pay to be gone, and I could keep them open in the Book a Year after they were gone, and the Purſer ſhould have their Victuals, and I their Wages; and in Forty ſuch Men, I ſhould Cheat my Dear Honeſt Maſter, whom the World admires, 500<abbr>
                     <hi>l</hi>
                  </abbr> and the Purſers Victuals Cheat my Maſter 200<abbr>
                     <hi>l</hi>
                  </abbr> and no body blamed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly.</hi> I could have Twenty Servants of my own, ſome paid Midſhips-Mans Pay; and all able, except two or three, to cover the reſt; and the brave Seamen that acted Midſhip-Men, ſhould ſome of them be payd, but able to diſcourage them, and make them mad, and my Maſter, it may be, he would be Cheated 100<abbr>
                     <hi>l</hi>
                  </abbr> in extraordinary Pay that way.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixthly,</hi> I could make out Tickets for many other Mens Pay; and if their Friends looked after them, it ſhould be <hi>ſpyum ſportum non ſpyum ſteallum;</hi> and if not found out, receive their Pay; if found out, my Wife or my Clerk had miſlaid them; and by this, Cheat the the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men themſelves of 350<abbr>
                     <hi>l</hi>
                  </abbr> and none Redreſs the Seamens Miſeries at laſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seventhly,</hi> If I ſaw an Enemies Ship, wink at it; eſpecially if ſhe was almoſt as ſtrong as I; and if my Seamen or Officers would not be Content, then Sail heavily after them until Night, and then Sail another Courſe, and ſo loſe them by Conſent, unleſs it were more minded.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eighthly,</hi> If I got a Merchant Ship that would hardly fight, and did therefore take her; if the Seamen had either a Sword, or any thing out of her as Prize after we had took her, I, or my Lieutenant would take it away from them, that the Seamen themſelves ſhould ſwear by their Damnation, If they ſee Twenty Ships, they would not ſpeak of it, ſince the Captains had moſt of the Plunder, and the poor Seamen Broken-Bones, or Death many of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ninthly,</hi> If but a Privateer or two came up with me, as they did to the <hi>Diamond,</hi> I could run into the Hold to ſave my Wretched, Debauched Life, for fear they ſhould ſhoot at our Ship before they took her: And if a Seaman ſhould offer to witneſs againſt me, I would have a Friend at the Council of War ſhould be ſure to Brow-beat the Seaman; and ſay to the Seaman, Sirrah, Where were you when the Captain went into the Hold? And if the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man had his Wits ready, he might anſwer, <hi>Between Decks, at my Gun, where I was Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered; and yet I need not fear being hanged theſe hard times; for the times are happily altered: For about Ten Years paſt Men might be hanged for nothing, and now they can hardly be hanged for Love or Money:</hi> And ſo Cowards and Knaves go unpuniſhed oftentimes.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:94714:6"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tenthly.</hi> I could Swear, and Damn, and Beat the Poor Seamen; and Beat my Officers, if they would not Beat the Seamen; and Cauſe the Poor Seamen to think, though they loved my Maſter dearly, yet they would run away, and loſe all their Pay rather than ſtay with me, to be abuſed like Dogs, although the Admirals were all good Men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eleventhly,</hi> I could Abuſe the Maſter, or it may be, keep him a Priſoner, while I knock my Ship on the Head, as the <hi>Mordant</hi> was, and yet come off well enough, by being Tryed by good Natured Commanders.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Twelfthly,</hi> If there were an Order that I ſhould Receive no Mans Pay but my own Servants, I could do well enough ſtill, and it may be better; for I could make out as many Tickets as before, and make Powers to them, Witneſſed by my Self and my Clerk, and leave Blanks for <hi>Jack-a-Noaks,</hi> and <hi>John-a-Styles,</hi> or it may be, my Wives Nurſe, or her Chair-Woman ſhould receive them; or it may be, ſell Three Hundred Pounds-worth to a Ticket-Buyer for One Hundred and Fifty Pound, and they would help me to Cheat my King and Countrey; and if One in Ten came to hear of it, when the Money was receiv'd, the Ticket-Buyer ſhould Hector them out of their Money; or it may be give them half ſo; that in Forty Pound diſcovered, they ſhould get it off for Twenty, and have at laſt One Hundred and Thirty Pound clear gain; and if I could get, as beforeſaid, Twelve Hundred Pound in a Voyage; and if other Captains would be like me, or if their Clerks were but Induſtriouſly Knaviſh, they might Cheat my Maſter and the Seamen half, ſo much as I could my ſelf; and ſo in One Hundred and Fifty Ships, the King may be Cheated of a Hundred Thouſand Pound the Year: But I hope the other Commanders would be honeſter: But I think of a Story; I had a certain Ticket call'd a Hog, and when it came to be payd, as I remember, they that were to pay it, ſaid, It was a Captains Hogg, and there was Twenty or Thirty in that Ship ſuch Hogs; and I could not but think of the Fancy, if I loſe my Money: For I ſuppoſe the Ship is allowed but Fifty Men; and thought, if Fifty Men produce Twenty Hogs, what may Fifty Thouſand do? That is Twenty Thouſand. And if one Hog with another be worth but Five Pound, I do think verily it will pay for as many Hogs as have been kil'd for the Fleet theſe Two Years; and I ſhould be ſorry if the Captains ſhould have ſo many Hogs, and in the mean time Six or Eight Thouſand Seamen run out of their Pay; therefore I do wiſh it were Fellony to receive a Seamans Money for time to come without a Lawful Power. And ſo I will take my leave of my Captains place, not being able to tell half my Cowardice and Knavery. And now if I were a Lieutenant of a Ship, and gave my mind to be Induſtrious: It may be, if I were not taken care of, I could act as follows.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> In going a Preſſing, get Forty ſhillings or Three Pound a Man, ſometimes of Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, when I had Catched them, to let them go again; and my Moſt Gracious Maſter ſhould have the Lame and the Lazy, and them that had not Money, or could not borrow any; and ſo I would get many a Guinea that way; and in the mean time it may be, I would be ſeveral Moneths in a Ketch to preſs Men for our Ship; and it may be, it ſhould coſt His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty Eighty or Ninety Pounds for the Veſſels here, and I would not carry on Board above a dozen Preſt-Men into our Ship; and it may be, ſometimes not above Five or Six Men for For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Pound Charge; and if the Accounts were Examined, it may be ſuch things may prove too true: And, it may be, my Captain would ſell ſome again for Three Guinaes a Man.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> It may be, the Colliers from <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> ſhould come Three Hundred Sail in a Voyage, and carry Three Thouſand Men, and they ſhould be ſearched; but I would take, it may be, a dozen of Salt Salmon, and a hundred Bottles of <hi>New-Caſtle</hi> Ale in a day; and it may be, when I had gotten what I could that way, get Two Guineas or Three of a Ship, to let that Pretty Old Man, or the other Pretty Lad alone; and it may be, that Fleet of Colliers ſhould pay extraordinary Wages, becauſe of the Preſs to Three Thouſand Men Six Thouſand Pound, and the King not get Fifty Men in the whole time out of them, and ſo the King and People all Cheated; and that is too bad indeed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I could make the Maſter of the Veſſel that I ſail with, inſtead of carrying off Preſt-Men for the King, to carry a Fraight of Coals for my uſe, as a Neighbour of mine was ſerved, and, I think, threatned to be kill'd into the Bargain, but he Unhorſed the Lieutenant.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> If it were after ſuch a time as that Brave Admirable <hi>Ruſſel</hi> did Burn the <hi>French</hi> Fleet, I could, if but one Ship to fit out, Preſs all over the City of <hi>London,</hi> and <hi>Suburbs,</hi> and the Colliers Trade to boot; and it may be, in the mean ſeaſon there might have been a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Fleet ſpared at the ſame time, ſo that the Tradeſmen of <hi>London</hi> ſhould not have one Moneths time in Three or Four Years: If I could help it free from having the Cuſtomers preſt away, although the <hi>French</hi> Fleet were beat; and if I could but have my Will, I could be a Scourge to many hundreds, and yet all for my own Profit, if not to abuſe the Subjects of the beſt of Kings, to make them groan or complain, and ſay, it was never ſo in <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> When I was on Board my Ship, I could beat and abuſe the Seamen, and call them Dogs, and Eternal Damned Dogs; and let them ſee, that if the Devil ſtir up Mankind to plague one another here, how ſad a Maſter he himſelf is. But however, as to this abuſing the men, I could not do that in ſome Ships; for ſome Commanders I could name, would not let me; and theſe Brave <hi>Engliſh</hi> hearted Commanders are ſuch as do really Incourage the Intereſt of our Gracious King <hi>William,</hi> and have Plenty of Seamen, and <hi>I</hi> honour them, though they know me not, and we have as brave Admirals as in the World.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:94714:7"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixthly,</hi> If <hi>I</hi> were, as <hi>I</hi> ſaid, Lieutenant, and other Officers according, we could beat the ordinary Fellows ſtoutly alſo, until Twenty or Thirty of them ſhould bind themſelves to me, and other Officers; and then, if they never did hardly a Pennyworth of work, they ſhould have able Pay, and ſo we ſhould get bravely, and the King pay for all, and all Cheated.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seventhly,</hi> If our Ship were to be paid, if the Captain would let me, <hi>I</hi> could get, it may be, Two or Three Guineas to let one of my own Gang of a Tradeſman come on Board at Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, and ſet Centuries to fire at all others, but whom he pleaſed to come with him; ſo that if this Tradeſman be never ſo great a Knave, yet the Poor miſerable Seamen muſt buy of him, or go to Sea without Cloaths; and if any honeſt man had truſted ſome of the Seamen before, if they come on Board but only to Receive their Debts, <hi>I</hi> would order the Centuries to fire at them, ſo that though <hi>I</hi> pretended to ſerve the King, <hi>I</hi> could act as if <hi>I</hi> would diſcourage all his Seamen that <hi>I</hi> could, and all that would truſt them, and ſo the Seamen ſhould be abuſed as much as poſſible, and have no more Credit in this Age of the World, if my Villany proſpered, and ſuch an Age never was before.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eighthly,</hi> It may be, if <hi>I</hi> pleaſed, <hi>I</hi> could abuſe the Maſter of our Ship, and he ſhould hardly ſay, his Soul was his own; and ſo Contradict him, that if the Ship were loſt, as madly as the Brave Shpip the <hi>Seadgmore</hi> was, yet there ſhould be no Body did it, and ſo no Body would be much blamed for it, let it be never ſo ſhamefully fooled away as that was.</p>
               <p>But now, If <hi>I</hi> were but a Purſer of a Ship, <hi>I</hi> could do many pretty Tricks alſo, if my Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain did not mind me, or hinder me: And that many do not, I am afraid, as they ſhould do in this Age.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt, I</hi> could, it may be, take up ſhort of my Sea-Store of Proviſions at my going out, and it may be, in Fourteen dayes after we were off from the Land, put the Seamen to ſhort Allowance; and then it may be,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Purchaſe at laſt their ſhort Allowance of many of them very Cheap, as follows; buy Twenty Shillings ſhort Allowance at Ten Shillings, pay them with a Gallon of Brandy at Ten Shillings that coſt me Five Shillings, and ſo get Fifteen Shillings; and in Two or Three Hundred Men that is Money indeed, if the Devil were not in it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> If Men dyed on Board, or on Shoar, charge them what Cloaths <hi>I</hi> pleaſe, becauſe they cannot anſwer for themſelves, and Cheat both Living and Dead.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly, I</hi> could, it may be, ſerve them as one Purſer <hi>Swain</hi> in the <hi>Roſe</hi> from <hi>New England</hi> ſerved an Acquaintance of mine; after his Ticket was made out clear of all Debts, and the Ticket ſold at Two Shillings in the Pound loſs, then charge in the Book Five Pound for To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacco to the Man before the Ticket was payd, and by this Trick <hi>I</hi> loſt Five Pound my ſelf. <hi>Probatum eſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> It may be, if my Captain and <hi>I</hi> could but hang together firſt, if my Captain would keep Twenty Men on the Book all the time we were out at Sea, though they were run away, <hi>I</hi> might get twenty times ten Pound by that trick alſo, and no body find it out.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixthly,</hi> If <hi>I</hi> were in the <hi>Straights,</hi> and my Captain would let me, <hi>I</hi> could pretend to buy Beveridge-Wine for the Seamen to mix with their Water inſtead of ſhort Allowance Beer: And <hi>I</hi> could buy Sower Decayed Wine that was almoſt like Vinegar, and one Hogſhead go as far as Four good ones, and ſo kill ſome of the Men with Gripes; and if the Captain would but be kept Drunk, <hi>I</hi> could help to find him Licquor; and if he did hear the Maſter and Chirurgeon Complain it had killed ſome Men, and it would kill the Reſt; and if the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain did but ſay, Let them dye and be damned, then <hi>I</hi> ſhould think my ſelf ſecure.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seventhly,</hi> If the Captain made out Forty or Fifty Tickets for Seamen, I muſt ſign them; and it may be, his Clerk; and I would ſmuggle twenty more, and get the Devil and all of Money that way: And <hi>I</hi> remember a Purſer, an Acquaintance of mine, told his Wife and <hi>I</hi> one day at Dinner, he brought home Nine Hundred Pound one Voyage: But ſaith he, by that time, <hi>I</hi> went to a Procurer, and got a Whore and a Bottle of Hedge-Wine, a Ticket was preſently gone: From whence <hi>I</hi> obſerve three things, by way of Diverſion: <hi>Firſt,</hi> Bad-got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Goods ſeldom do proſper. And <hi>Secondly,</hi> As the Gentleman ſaid by his Monkey, A Bad Life, and a bad End. And <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That which is got over the Devils back, is apt to be ſpent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his belly: And that is bad Intereſt indeed, and yet Dayly Improved.</p>
               <p>But now, If <hi>I</hi> ſhould tell all the tricks that could be play'd to get Money in a Purſers Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, it might cauſe the Price to riſe double before <hi>I</hi> purchaſe one; but however, they muſt remember to be kind to the Commanders, in giving them Freſh Proviſion: And ſo much for the <hi>Trade</hi> of a Cheating Purſer. And <hi>I</hi> ſuppoſe thoſe that are honeſt need not be offended with me, for it hurts not them, if they have not a ſore place: A little Rubbing of others will do them no hurt to be ſure; and if any do ſeem to be hurt, <hi>I</hi> ſhall fear it is ſomething amiſs with him, but if he ſmiles in my face and is pleaſed, I will then conclude he is a ſound Man. And ſo much to that; the Honeſt will be glad, if others be mended.</p>
               <p>But as to the Gunners, the Honeſt Men, I hope will not be diſpleaſed to hear ſome have been ſuch Fools to play the Thief, until they were hanged for ſtealing of their Maſters Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: But I wonder how it ſhould almoſt come to Light, for I do not remember that ever <hi>I</hi> heard of one pennyworth of Profit any one had to diſcover any goods ſtolen from His Majeſty; and <hi>I</hi> fear, if any Seamen diſcover it, they muſt expect rather to be beat by ſome ſmall Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers then Rewarded with Preferment for diſcovering the Theft of the Gunners; but I do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94714:8"/>one Gunner had hidden Seventy Four Barrels of Powder; and Honeſt Loyal Captain <hi>Mitchel</hi> made his Men ſearch twice, and at laſt found it, and ſent the Gunner to the <hi>Marſhalſeas,</hi> and he came off, becauſe it was not ſold away: And I think the Carpenter and Gunner of the <hi>Exeter</hi> were like to have come ſhort home; but it ſeems they had others to Convey away their Prize, and ſo eſcaped firſt: But the next time being not long after, the Gunners Powder took fire, and blowed up near a Hundred Men, and ſo the Pretty Gunner was hanged, for all there was but Twenty Barrels of Powder: And if a Man ſhould multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply and divide by the Rule of Loſs and Gain with time. If one Ship ſteal Twenty Barrels, and another Ship hide Seventy Barrels, what may One Hundred and Fifty Ships do? And if One Year do ſo much, what may Seven Years do? And the Price of Powder, I do hear, was Fifteen Pound the Barrel at <hi>New England</hi> before the <hi>Nonſuch</hi> came away, and I judge the Gunner bought none, neither was I there to ſee him fell any; but the Ship is gone to <hi>France,</hi> with what's left; and as to the <hi>Breda,</hi> being blown up with about Four Hundred People on Sunday Morning, I do ſuppoſe the Gunner of her, or ſome of their Company was a going to Church, or ſomething otherwiſe in the Powder-Room; but His Majeſty loſt a Brave Ship, a Brave Commander, and as Brave Men as moſt in the Fleet; and I do wonder, if the Gunner of the <hi>Elizabeth</hi> had carryed away his Seventy Barrels of Powder, how he would have paſt his Accounts: But I remember a Story of an Old Gunner, dead ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral years paſt, That if a Man were as juſt as <hi>Job,</hi> there muſt be Money; and if he were as very Thief as any in <hi>Newgate,</hi> Money, Money, Money; I ſay no more. But ſuppoſe, if I were Store-keeper at ſome place, like to our Garriſon of <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> I could agree with the Gunners to go half Snips; and we would ſell our Powder to a Merchant-Man, and ſend it away at Noon-day; and Fortune often favours the Bold, ſo that it might ſucceed; and if taken, it was ſo many Barrels ordered for ſuch a Ship: and if the Gunner of the Man of War own it, and it went clear the Merchant-Man had it, and ſo the Gunner and I would drink Friends; and hardly any one ever think of it, or mind us</p>
               <p>But in my Opinion, if there were a Law made, That both the Thieves and the Receivers ſhould be alſo ſerved alike, and alſo thoſe Hoy-Men, or others, that helped to Convey it away; and I ſuppoſe the pretty Creatures need not be hanged, for now People are not willing to teſtifie againſt ſuch to take away their Lives perhaps; but if there were a Law made, That if any were found guilty of ſtealing, or conveying away the Kings Goods, that they that are guilty ſhall have the Middle Joynt of their Finger on each Hand next the little one cut off to mark them, and then let them be ſold to <hi>Virginia,</hi> or ſome other Plantation for perpetual Slaves; and to take Security of the Merchants here, that they ſhall Tranſport them; and the Buyers beyond Sea, to give Securities to the Governour there, to keep them during their Lives; and if any of them do make their Eſcape, then on their firſt Landing in <hi>England</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to be hanged; and that Maſter of a Ship that brought them again, to have his Finger on each Hand cut off, and he to be ſold in their Room: And if the many ſorts of Thieves in <hi>England</hi> were all ſerved ſo, it might peradventure, clear <hi>England</hi> of Thieves in Five or Six Years time, ſince the <hi>Motto</hi> of theirs is, <hi>A Short Life and a Sweet:</hi> And they have got a Trick to caſt off their Shoes ſome of them when they are hanged, becauſe they will not dye in their Shoes; and therefore their ſhort Life and Sweet ſhould be turned into a Long Life and Bitter, and then they would rather work here at firſt, than be alwayes Slaves; and this Medicine would, it may be, ſerve Clippers and Coiners: But in my Opinion, they that furniſh them with Broad Money, and help off with the Small, are the greateſt Villains; ſince it is Repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a Poor Fellow will work for half a Crown a day a Clipping of Money; and for Thieving many bring up their Children from Six or Seven Years old to it; and People are unwilling to Proſecute them ſometimes, for fear of their Death; but this would prevent that fear: But this is out of my way of a Gunners Imployment, except I am a Thief alſo; and then I ſhould have many other things to ſteal beſides Powder too many to enumerate here: And if I were a Boatſwain, as I ſhould have Charge of abundant of things, ſo might ſteal the more; but it may be, their neateſt way would be, if I could get the Store-keepers to be but Confederates with me, I might not need to ſteal the things my ſelf, perhaps he will ſell them for me: But I cannot imagine how we could Convey away a Cable of Twenty Inches worth near 100 <abbr>
                     <hi>l</hi>
                  </abbr> and ſell it for F<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urteen or Fifteen Pound: I fear this would be paſt my skill, although I have Converſed with many Thouſands this War, and been on Board of almoſt all the Ships His Majeſty had, ſome Three or Four Years paſt; but I have a bad Memory, and apt to forget above half my Skill; only, if I were a Boatſwain, and muſt Sign the Seamens Tickets, if my Captain had Forty Hogs, I ſhould expect to have ſome Two or Three Pigs, except I had been found out to have Cheated the King of ſome Stores, and the Captain winked at that, and then in Civility I muſt let his Hogs paſs free, and one kindneſs doth deſerve another among good Natur'd Men; and of all Mankind, theirs are the moſt true one to another, if they go to the Gallows, nay to Hell, they will commonly keep Counſel: And if I were a <hi>Carpenter,</hi> I might improve my Talent, as other Officers, to ſteal ſomething out of a Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred things; for I ſign no Tickets to get Hogs and Pigs; and if I were a Maſter of a Man of War, I could not tell what to ſteal; but if I ſigned the Seamens Tickets, as I muſt do in my place, if the Captain or his Clerk do Cheat the King and the Seamen of Fifty Hogs, I
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:94714:9"/>ſhould expect to take Tithe, to have at leaſt Four or Five beſides my Supernumerary Servants; and this, and being Drunk or Mad, and letting a Ship be knockt on the Head, is the greateſt Feats of this Age that I could think of at preſent. But if I were a Miniſter in a Ship, I could make a ſhift to be a diſgrace to the moſt Excellent National Church in the World; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of Reading Prayers often, and Preaching, and Reproving the Seamen for their Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, I could keep Company Night and Day with the Worſt Officers in the Ship, and Drink and Swear as faſt as they; and ſo diſhonour my Holy Profeſſion: But if the Honourable Houſes of Parliament paſs an Act againſt Swearing, Curſing, and Blaſpheming, I hope there will be ſome better Regulation in the Minds of Mankind: And as there is as Able and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Biſhops, as hath been for this Laſt Age of the World: It would be a very acceptable Work to God, and to the Church, to ſend Sober, and Sound, and Couragious Miniſters on Board the Fleet: And as to the preventing of the Thievery in the Fleet, if there were but this incouragement, That whenever any Seaman could diſcover any Goods of the Kings to be Stollen, or Conveyed away in order to Steal, that in ſuch a Caſe, thoſe Two or Three Seamen that ſhould make Diſcovery of it, and that the Goods were found out, then the ſaid Seamen ſhould have their own Pay ordered to be payd them, and have a free Diſcharge out of the Ship, and a Protection from the Preſs for a Years time; there would be Seamen enough to watch the Stealing of any Stores, and the firſt two diſcoverers, might have alſo half the Value of the Goods diſcovered, and the Officer that purloyned it, to loſe his Pay, and be ſent into ſome of the I lantations for his Life-time, to learn to be Honeſt: And it may be, he would be ſo, when Two of his Thieving Fingers were cut off for a Medicine and Mark. And for the Captains Clerks, I do think, they have Cheated ſo many People this War, beſides Chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the beſt of Kings; I think there ought to be Five Hundred Pound Security that they ſhould give, that they ſhall not Cheat the King or the Seamen by getting Tickets wrongfully made out: I remember Two or Three of them told me they had opportunity to make out many Powers, they having near a hundred People in each Ship that had been dead or gone away, that they did think none would look after: But I adviſed them to beware; for, ſaid I, if their Friends here you Received their Money, you may be ſued for it Seven Years hence, except you will be Vagabonds, and Run your Countrey, beſides Cheating the Living and the Dead: But whither they took my Counſel is unknown to me; one is gone to Eternity, and the other I think is now a Captain himſelf: But however, I think it were the way to ſave abundance of Money to the King Honeſtly, to make it Fellony for any to come to Receive a Seamans Pay wrongfully, or to detain their Tickets wrongfully, and would be much better than that ſad Trick of making all the Poor Honeſt Miſerable Seamen run, that by Sickneſs or Death cannot get aboard their own Ships again when they are ſet Sick on the Shoar, and their Ships leave them: And among all the Miſteries I have been ſpeaking of, it is pitty ſo much ſhould be excuſed, and the Seamens Miſeries only aggravated with Miſery: And I will ſpeak ſomething of my skill, how I could abuſe the Miſerable Seamen, if I were Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of a Merchant-Man; and that ſeveral wayes; as Back-beating of them, and Belly-bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of them; and at laſt, after a Miſerable Voyage, keep them Ten or Twelve Weeks out of their Pay, and abate them at leaſt Two or Three Moneths Pay right or wrong; and if they will not take it, let them go to Law for it, and ſpend half their Pay; and this Curſed Cuſtom may bring a Curſe on much Navigation, if not prevented by ſome Law; for now it is very Common, and Poor Seamens Families do want that Money to buy Bread that ſome of their Maſters Cheat them off: And indeed, there did uſe to be a pretence of Dammage for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly: And if a Poor Beggarly Fellow that was not worth Four Pence, could get any Men to buy an old Ship fit for nothing but to break up, or to carry to Sea, to drown Rats and Mice; ſuch a Fellow would take in Merchants Goods; and if the Ship did ſwim, and came home again, though the Seamen pumped, it may be, Ten Dayes together, to ſave their Ship and Lives, yet if the Goods were damnified with Wet, the Poor Miſerable Seamens Wages, which could hardly ſave the Ship, yet they muſt pay for the Dammage; and now there is many ſtop part of their Poor Seamens Pay, although there be not any Dammage; and it may be, that ſhall buy the Maſters Wife a Silk Gown; or it may be, help him to Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a whore, with as much Confidence as ſome Commiſſion Officers do; and in my mind, that is too ſawcy for Maſters of Merchant Men to pretend to: But they that are honeſt themſelves, will pay their Men honeſtly, and theſe Maſters I Love and Eſteem, and they are a Credit and Incouragement to our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Navigation: And I have known ſeveral Brave Worthy Men Commanders of <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Ships, and other Voyages who have fed their Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men well, and payd them well, and God hath Bleſſed them with Riches, and with the Love of the Seamen alſo: But it is a ſad thing how ſome others do act: For is it poſſible for a Commander of an <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Ship to have ſo Little, and ſo Bad Provitions, and to deny them ſuch Neceſſary Subſiſtance, that there might be ſeveral Men in a Ship really periſh for want? I have heard of near Twenty Men have been ſuppoſed to periſh in a Ship that way, when Sixty or Seventy Men have not been allowed a Pound of Butter to their Water-Gruel, and not Two Pound of Sugar; And when the Chirurgeon of the Ship hath Complained, the Captain hath ſaid, Doctor, What need you trouble your ſelf: And in my Judgment, it is a ſad thing alſo, that they ſhould not be ſo well provided with matter, as the Hogs are in the Ship: And it was a ſhame, that the <hi>Modena</hi> from <hi>India</hi> that is now miſſing, ſhould be forced to borrow
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:94714:10"/>Water of other Ships, ſo ſoon almoſt as ſhe came out of her laſt Harbour, where they might have had Water enough; and if ſhe be loſt for want of Water, I ſuppoſe her loſs to the Company will be near One Hundred and Fifty Thouſand Pound; and to the King near Twenty Thouſand Pound: And were it not for Luker of Stowage, and Freight of Goods, that it may be, every Tun of Water might hinder the Stowage of near a Tun of Goods; and ſo the Captain might loſe about Twelve Pound Freight; I know not what other Reaſon can be reaſonably rendred for ſuch bad Uſage to be put on Men, to deny them Water, that God alloweth to Man and Beaſt: And indeed, in my Opinion, it was a very Dreadful thing, that any Captain ſhould be Charged with hurrying of his Chirurgeon out of the World laſt Voyage, by taking him out of his Bed, and Keell-halling of him, that is, it ſeems, to put him down on one ſide of the Ship into the Water, and Dragging him up on the other, when he was a Sweating; and that he dyed in two dayes afterward. Now ſurely, We are at Land the freeſt People in the World; and it is pity that ſuch Cruel Barbarouſneſs ſhould be uſed on the Water, that any Commanders ſhould not only Barbarouſly abuſe their Ships-Company, but kill them, as ſome have been accuſed of; beſides many others ſuppoſed to dye for want of Food ſufficient to ſupport Nature: And it would be happy for the Poor Miſerable Wretched Seamen, if they had but as good Plenty of Food and Water, as the Captains Hogs have in ſome Ships: And if there were a ſearch into the <hi>Eaſt-India-Companies</hi> Ships Books, I ſuppoſe there were ſome Ships carried out about One Hundred and Seventy, or One Hundred and Eighty Men apiece, and brought home but about Thirty, or about Thirty Five of thoſe they Carryed out: And if the Books of the <hi>Beaufort</hi> and the <hi>Rocheſter</hi> were Examined, it might fall out to be them, or ſome ſuch; and the <hi>Sampſon</hi> hired near Fifty <hi>Indians</hi> to help bring her home: And if from the Year 1675, until the Years 1690, the <hi>Eaſt-India-Companies</hi> Ships have Buried a quarter part, if not above half the Men they carryed out of <hi>England</hi> with them, then the Honourable Houſes will ſee how greatly they Increaſed Seamen in Fifteen Years time; and if they carryed out not above a quarter part of Goods thither that they did in Value bring home again to <hi>England,</hi> then it may be ſuppoſed there was much Silver and Gold went for the Reſt; and indeed, who could ever think that we ſhould have our Guineas Riſe to paſs at Twenty Five Shillings the piece; and that if we have Ten Millions of Silver-Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, that there ſhould be Four Millions Clipt off from it; and yet that Silver ſhould be ſo dear, that our Mild-Money is worth Twelve-pence in the Pound Profit to melt down; and this is the fruit of our having Two Millions of Goods more from <hi>France,</hi> or otherwiſe, in times of Peace; ſome Years more than they had of us: And, until we have a New Coinage for our Money, I fear it will be ſo ſtill, if Peace comes: But however, if our Old Money continue to be Clipt as it is, we ſhall keep that, and have abundance of Counterfeit alſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to it. But if there were Money ordered to be Coined, that were Three Hundred Ounces for a Hundred Pound Sterling-Money, it would be heavier by a third part than our Clipt-Money; and a Million of Mild Coined in a Year at that weight, would call in another Million of Old, and have a Million and a half of good New Money in the room of a Million of Old; and no Charge to the Nation; and there might be One <hi>per Cent.</hi> allowed to the Bank, or the <hi>Goldſmiths,</hi> or the <hi>Chamber</hi> of <hi>London</hi> to carry in Silver, and have it out every Moneth, would be Twelve <hi>per Cent. per Annum:</hi> But this is by the way of Diverſion; for I was pleading for the poor miſerable Seamen: If there was Incouragement for them to be Victualled con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, as well in all Merchant-Ships, as the King doth Victual in the Royal Navy; and if they were payd fully for all that was pinched out of their Bellyes; and alſo that none ſhould be abated any thing out of their Pay and Wages for Dammage, except it were for their own neglect: This would be the way to keep the Seamen from running out of the Land in time of Peace; and alſo that there might be ſome way found out, that they might have their Wages of Merchant-Ships, without going to Law half a Year, or a Year; and that they might not be kept out of their Money near a quarter of a Year after they are come home, as ſome of the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Ships do: And ſeeing that the Poor Souls have been out many of them Two or Three Years, and are Preſt into His Majeſties Service, I do wonder how the Commanders can think the poor miſerable Seamen muſt do for Cloths to fit them out in His Majeſties Service, if His Majeſties Ships goeth out to Sea in half that time before they are paid: In my mind, this is far from the Law of God to the <hi>Jews,</hi> that were not to Let the Hire of the Labourers reſt unpaid one Night, <hi>Leviticus</hi> 19.30. And that becauſe their Heart was ſet upon it, and indeed the Lord himſelf did take care for the Beaſt under the Law, that the Oxen that did tread out the Corn, ſhould not be muſled: But if I miſtake not, If the Honourable Houſes will ſee one of the Bonds of a Hundred Pound a piece, that the Seamen ſhall not carry out any Woollen Cloth, neither near Forty other ſorts of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Goods out of <hi>England</hi> to <hi>India:</hi> neither bring home any <hi>Silks</hi> or <hi>Callicoes;</hi> neither near Forty other ſorts of Goods from thence; it may be, they will ſee the Seamen are thereby muſled more than God would allow the Oxen to be. And many times in thoſe Long Voyages, if half the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men were to periſh for want, they have not Forty Shillings apiece Venture to buy any thing to ſave their Lives: And it doth ſo fall out in thoſe Voyages, that at Three or Four Years end, when the Poor Miſerable Seamen do come home, they have not ſome of them Forty Shillings apiece to Receive, the other being due, as is pretended to the Captain or Purſers, or ſome Officers or another, except it be Two moneths or Threes Pay that is paid at the <hi>Eaſt-India-Houſe,</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:94714:11"/>and that ſhould be payd one Moneth every Six; and ſometimes their Poor Wives or others are forced to wait near Six Moneths more after it is due; and it may be, wait Three or Four Hours in a day ſometimes into the bargain. I have wondred at the Miſery of the Poor in that Caſe, if a Woman waſheth and ſcowreth for her Living, ſhe may loſe the Earning one good part of the Value of a Moneths Pay in looking after it; and I do won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company can ſee or hear of the Miſery of the Poor Seamens-Wives or Relations waiting ſo tediouſly, and not have their hearts melt for their Miſeries: I do know that <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>A good Man is merciful to his Beaſt:</hi> But I do remember another Scripture ſaith, <hi>The tender Mercies of the wicked are cruel.</hi> And I do remember, that Excellent Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Doctrine of Chriſt, the Marrow of the Law and Prophets that is taught our Children in the Church-Catechiſme, <hi>To do to all Men as we would be done unto:</hi> And if thoſe in this Age that can let the Miſeries of the Miſerable be Increaſed and Delighted in, were ſo ſerved them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, they would think it Miſerable to have not one Penniworth of Bread at home; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it may be One Shilling hardly of Credit, and to be made Run Thirty times Three or Four Miles for Twenty or Thirty Shillings, as it may be, ſome do ſeveral Moneths after it is due, ſeems very miſerable: And I do remember, God ſaid of <hi>Jeruſalem, Wo to the oppreſſing City.</hi> And I do wonder ſometimes, how this Age can delight to ſee the Miſery of the Poor, as I know ſome cannot but ſee in ſeveral places, where my buſineſs hath led me, to ſee poor Wretches waiting by great multitudes in great Diſtreſs and Poverty; it hath been ready to fetch Tears from my Eyes: And I have ſometimes thought, ſurely our Moſt Gracious God will ariſe for the Cry of the Poor and Sighing of the Needy; and 'tis the Cauſe of the moſt miſerable ſort of Poor in <hi>England.</hi> I have been pleading, and hope God will graciouſly Incline the Two moſt Honourable Houſes to pity their Caſe: And I can no more tell the Tenth part of the miſery of the Seamens Families, then I can tell the tenth part of the villany of ſome others, who either do Cheat the King or Abuſe the Seamen: And if the Two moſt Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Houſes can find out a way to Relieve the one, and puniſh the others, it may ſave the King and the Poor Seamen, peradventure, much loſs for time to come; and if in any little hints <hi>I</hi> have given of any thing, it ſhall be thought worth while to Inquire more after it, if the Lord our Gracious God and Merciful Father pleaſe to Preſerve and Aſſiſt me, I ſhall be willing to give farther Light into ſome things, and that without Prejudice to any One Living: For I bleſs the Lord, I am in Charity with all Mankind, and do not know any but are ſo with me: And for my King and Countrey, I would ſerve them both faithfully for Love, and without any deſign againſt either: For I do think, that they that would now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray the King and Countrey, now that God hath by his Miraculous Hand United us thus, are by their Treachery void of Grace and Reaſon, and Common Sence: And if His moſt Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Majeſty will, theſe Three Nations, and all the Confederates ſo heartily United, have enough to do to deal with that common Plague of his own Subjects, and the Chriſtian World, the <hi>French</hi> King: I wonder who would defend our Treacherous Dealers againſt the <hi>French,</hi> if like Spannels they were layd under the <hi>French</hi> Kings Paws, who hath Ruined all the Proteſtant Intereſt in his own Nation, that helped him to keep in his own Throne: And he hath been a Plague to Proteſtants and Papiſts round about him; and to think he would be kind to a Proteſtant Church here, is all Nonſenſe or Malice; and my Fathers Two Dogs in <hi>Kent</hi> had more Senſe alwayes; for though they did, it may be, ſnarl ſometimes about a Bone, they alwayes did, and would Unite againſt the <hi>Tanners</hi> Dog, who would beat any one of them, but they alwayes joyned together, and beat him: This is a homely Compariſon, but a Real Truth; I have ſeen it: And indeed it is ſaid by the Prophet, <hi>The Ox knoweth his Owner, and the Aſs his Maſters Crib:</hi> And I think hardly any Beaſts or Aſſes in the World would betray ſuch good Paſture as we have in <hi>England,</hi> into the hands of the worſt ſort of Beaſts of Prey: And if I do not miſtake, in my Judgment, the <hi>French</hi> King and his People are like a Body that hath the Rickets, that hath a great Head and great Arms, but poor Crooked Legs, hardly able to bear up the Head and Arms; and would hardly have ſtood until this time; but they have gotten many Treacherous Tools to help to Splinter them up: And I think the <hi>French</hi> in Ruining of his People, makes Soldiers as Naturally, as any Gentlemen can make Tobacco-Stoppers at a Coffee-Houſe, by breaking of whole Pipes: So, If the <hi>French</hi> Ruine a Family, it may be, he makes Two Soldiers; both Father and Son muſt go for Soldiers, or Starve: But Bleſſed be the Lord, that is not our Caſe: The Pooreſt People in <hi>England</hi> live ſo well moſt of them, that they are not forced to go for Soldiers; and they that go for Love, it is pity that any of them ſhould be Cheated of part of their Pay: And another thing now at the end of the Chapter is this, That thoſe who get good Mens Children by way of wheedle, and Liſt them; and after will ſell them to their Parents, or Friends, or Wives for Three Guineas, or Five Guineas, or Ten Pound, is a great deal worſe than Robbing on the High-way: A Neighbour of mine did ſell many ſo; and a Stranger that had gotten a Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers Son in <hi>Kent,</hi> a Relation of mine would have Sold him me for Three Guineas; But though I did know the Cheat, I would not hinder His Majeſties Service; for I ſaid it was as good a Cauſe as ever was in <hi>England;</hi> And ſo I ſuppoſe, the King payd Three Pound for the ſame man, I might have had for Three Guineas; and if I had bought him, I ſuppoſe they would have Introduced themſelves into other Companies, and Liſted another in his room, and ſo had Six Pound and Six Shillings of His Majeſty and my ſelf: But may it pleaſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:94714:12"/>Your Houours, though I know how the King and Countrey may be abuſed at Sea, I am more Ignorant how he is Cheated by Land: But I do verily believe, there is ſo much of that, as it will not be half found out this Seven Years: And indeed, I think we ſhould be the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieſt People under the Face of the Heavens, if we knew the worth of our Mercies, and were true to our King and Countrey: We are, Bleſſed be the Lord, Happy in our King, who is a Lyon in the Field, with as True Courage, as ever any of the Brave Heroes of Old had; and as much Mildneſs on the Throne, as ever any <hi>Engliſh</hi> King had, and ſeems to be the Darling of Heaven and Good Men: And we are happy in Loyal and Faithful Lords and Commons in Parliament, and might be ſo with our ſelves, if we did not ſtudy Wit and Knavery more than Wiſdom and Honeſty: And for my own part, I muſt beg for Pardon for all my Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Folly in Repreſenting theſe things: And indeed, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Ye ſuffer Fools glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſeeing ye your ſelves are wiſe:</hi> And it may be, ſome things that are fooliſhly Repreſented, may have Coſt His Majeſty, and the People of the Nation, ſome Hundreds of Thouſands of Pounds to Pay for in ſome Years paſt: And if that His Majeſty would Graciouſly be pleaſed to Order out a Committee, and His Majeſty would ſend out His Proclamation, That all Seamen that have had their Pay Received wrongfully, and their Tickets Detained wrongfully; and that if they have been ſo ſerved, they ſhall have Redreſs; And if they have ſince this War actually run away, and yet their Pay is Received by the Captains Clerks or others; that the Seamen ſhall on their Information of the Kings being Cheated thereby, have their own ſelves excuſed, and have leave to Sue them that have Cheated ſo the King of their Pay: And that without Charge at Law, by being heard freely: And if alſo the ſaid Committee ſhould have leave to hear how much Money hath been Received, as Bribes to excuſe Seamen from the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reſs; and that the Seamen or Maſter ſhall have their Money again of the Officers or Commanders who took it; and if Complaints were heard freely, it might be a likely means and way to inform the Honourable Houſes, that it would be worth while to make Laws againſt Cheating the King and Countrey, and againſt Buying and Selling the Kings Subjects, either by Land or Sea, and alſo againſt many other Enormities that cannot be eaſily Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented: And for my Miſtakes in the manner of Repreſenting, I beg Pardon: But for the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of it, I fear this Age knows it to be miſerably true. And now I commit what I have written to the Bleſſing and Protection of our Moſt Gracious Lord God, from whom I do heartily beg Mercy for His Majeſty and all Your Honours, and for all theſe Nations; and that in the Bleſſing of God on theſe Nations, He, and all Your Honours, and me, and all my Family may be ſafe for all Time and all Eternity. <hi>And to the Eternal God the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit, Three Perſons, and One Glorious God, be the Everlaſting Honour, Glory and Praiſe to Eternity,</hi> Amen. So Prays</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>His Majeſties Faithful Loving Subject, And Your Honours Faithful and Loving Servant, And Old <hi>England</hi>'s Loving and Faithful Inhabitant, and not Betrayer, <hi>William Hodges.</hi>
                  </signed>
                  <dateline>Hermitage-Bridge, <date>Feb. <hi>22. 1694.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
